back Bounty is not a get rich quick ski
beginnings of back Bounty are very
difficult that's what many people say
about back Bounty and I agree with them
but there are always outliers and one of
them is Johan Karsten who is already
making six digit income from back Bounty
while only start having started one and
a half years ago and he does it part
time while also having a wife and three
children
I have so many questions to ask him so
without further Ado enjoy the episode
hello Johan thank you so much for for
joining me in the podcast if you could
introduce yourself to our viewers and
tell us how did you get to the point you
are in start wherever you want to start
yeah thank you um hello uh thank you for
having me here uh so my name is Juan
Carlson uh I go by the the handle of the
u-wax car it's just like an abbreviation
of my name
um with my middle name in between
uh that's my handle on Twitter and also
on hacker one where I do most of my bug
hunting which is probably why I'm here
um I
started bug hunting for
I think it's two years ago now
um I started with the gitlab and I've
been continuing mainly hunting on the
gitlab since then
and I've climbed to top four aiming for
top three soon at the GitHub
list so yeah that's it that's a huge
achievement so congratulations I I often
uh write in in the newsletter that
we should look habits at people who are
most knowing the industry the biggest
authorities that everyone knows but also
we should be more focused on people who
are just a few steps a year two years
before us and that's why I I look up at
you as the example because you're
the way you climbed the leaderboard on
gitlab is is absolutely uh amazing but
before we get to that uh what is your
background in terms of education and
your current job
yeah so my my background is a bit like
scattered I guess like I
I I've grown up as like a a tech Kitty
here in Sweden like a lot of kids in the
80s yeah you know it is like I was born
87. uh so I had computers pretty early
and access to Internet pretty early and
I was mainly focusing on playing games
and uh downloading them for free of
course and uh
and doing all that stuff that we did in
the 90s and early 2000s
um
I then also went to like high school I
guess would be the equivalent here in
Sweden like in a tech tech high school
so I did like programming in the Java
1.6 and some Cisco courses and stuff
like that in high school
then I kind of decided to leave
computers alone and I decided to like
never touch them again and I want went
for like one year of military service
that we had in Sweden back then like
mandatory uh and then I applied for art
school and I did like art studies for
about eight years or something like that
six seven eight years and then I'm
got my first kid and I started to
realize that I also had to earn money
and then I like dusted off my old CV
from high school and got the they were
really nice to me at like the Stockholm
University and gave me a job as like a
computer system administrator is taking
care of some computers there and I did
that for like two years and then I
decided to go to university again and
take a bachelor in like computer science
to get like a better Foundation
and that's also when I did you get get
the job like in it straight after the
art studies they get it right yeah like
it was like in the like humanist
Department like uh the language uh
Center at the Stockholm University so
they kind of liked that I knew something
about computers but I also had like this
uh software uh like we're into like
philosophy and those kind of studies uh
so I kind of like smiled my way in there
I guess but I always had like some sort
of like I've always been like the family
computer guy like fixing things but I I
hadn't like been actively doing like
programming or scripting or stuff like
that before that uh so that was like a
lucky lucky chance for them and
it worked out and uh what happened after
after the university yeah so like last
year of University I I got to enroll
into like you had to like choose some
separate courses that was not like in
your real curriculum and at Stockholm's
like a kth like the Royal technology
University uh in Stockholm there's this
course called like ethical hacking which
is quite popular and it seems super
interesting and I so I enrolled into
that one and that whole course is like a
a big CTF candle like there's like this
big virtual Network where you're
supposed to find a lot of flags and if
you find all the flags you pass the
course uh it's uh yeah and it was like a
really amazing experience I thought like
it was super fun I found all the flags
without any hints and I was really proud
I spent like way too much time on it and
like discarded all other courses I had
at the time and then I I with the help
from that the teacher there who held
that course he also
helped me like getting this like thesis
and he was like my thesis advisory
which I then did so my thesis project
was to do like a a security assessment
of some part of
gitlab so that was like what we nailed
down mainly focusing on the the graphql
API of gitlab but
um so that was when I got introduced to
bug band this because gitlab had like a
white Bandit program and
we knew that like if we find anything we
can
apply it all right send it in to them
but I I hadn't like ever heard of it
before that so that's about like two and
a half years ago or something like that
what would be in the thesis if you would
not find any vulnerability in gitlab
yeah I think that's that's think that's
what gave me the this great like Head
Start into bike bounties because the
thesis like
you could pass the thesis even if you
didn't find anything like the the only
thing you have to achieve was to write
like some sort of like
thorough uh and thoroughly like
Motivated Security assessment like you
could prove like you had done most of
the steps like doing like a threat
analysis and a reading old
uh like previous
reports maybe getting like an
understanding of the history of security
inside of gitlab and
so it gave me like I think the course
the right writing this thesis is like
two months or something
or two and a half
uh so it gave me like you just have to
do this for these months if you don't
find anything that's fine you just have
to write like a report and you have to
do it like thoroughly
and as it is like or like as it happens
with bug about this like if you spend
two months on something
you hopefully will be able to find
something like at least something that
is like starting to look like a bug
uh
the reason I'm asking is because uh when
I was doing my thesis we were my friend
also wanted to to do some security
research
um but like we were advised that
in case we should portray the way that
we are writing tools and finding bugs
would be a bonus but it's not necessary
and of course what we ended up doing is
only the tools and nothing else
um we tried a bit but but we focused on
the part that we had to do so uh so
that's when I why I envy you for for
finding the battery subject and actually
finding finding pullbacks no we actually
we had like we got like I was doing this
with like a third party which I cannot
really disclose like who it was but they
they gave us like three options of like
this uh semi-open Source or like
projects to look at that they were
interested in and they had like matter
most git lab and like UB key
uh and we felt like matter most would be
like or like our guide a guide tells us
like uh yeah matter most that would be
like uh slamming in open doors I don't
think that's true but he meant like
that's not really like there's not as
many people looking at it and then we
looked at like ubiky and it seemed like
way too advanced for us so then we just
like it was just like by luck that we
ended up like in the middle like gitlab
felt like a
a good like Middle Ground between them
if there are any students listening to
us who are considering a subject for
their thesis and they want to to do
something similar what would you
recommend them to do
uh
yeah I'm like
definitely go for something uh
open source and with like the great
thing about gitlab is that everything is
open so you can read all the reports or
and you can see all the code changes and
you can see the discussions inside of
gitlab and so that makes it way easier
to actually get content for a report
or something like that and like you can
take a lot of like different paths like
doing code assessment or running and you
also have the ability to like set up
your own environment and stuff like that
so any sort of like open source things
would be easier I know also you're
allowed to speak about it like
afterwards so because otherwise it's
really hard to write a good report that
was one of the issues that we debated
like in the beginning like if you find
anything will we even be allowed to
write about this or not
yeah and also it's it's a funny thing
when you find something in open source
but the report is not disclosed yet
so the issue in theory is public and if
you weren't the submitter you could
easily go ahead and reverse the the
commit with the pageant and make a
write-up but considering you are the the
author you can't really do it but yeah
but we know that gitlab uh this classes
a lot of things that uh I think they
always agree to to disclose the report
but yeah I mean if if you're not
disclose it you can always go to their
uh the the issue tracker and you can
find them there so is this public as
well yeah they they make like everything
a public after 30 days under issue
tracker so okay so yeah so you can find
a lot more there uh that's a good tip
for anyone
that much easier and apart from the the
scores of the CTF which you mentioned
which sounds really good
um what resources did you use to learn
about cyber security and back Bounty
specifically
uh
a lot of
Port swiger of course like athlete
strike reading I haven't done that money
like labs and stuff like that uh and the
other than that like a lot of just blogs
like Googling for Concepts and reading a
lot of blogs and also the the hacker one
like activity feed
and also then scenes like last year also
Twitter has been like a big
uh source of information for me like
getting hints to like what to look at
and what to
um
so I I haven't really I haven't taken
like courses or certifications or
read that many like books or anything I
bought some but I haven't really read
them yet
I bought some courses as well and I
haven't finished them either
so it's it's hard to have started yeah
yeah
um and how do you differentiate the good
quality resources from the bad quality
resources
yeah that's uh that's a tricky question
I I like when
when things uh get like into the deep
Concepts behind like reading a write-up
that is just like uh telling you some
steps uh that could be like a good start
but then I always try to find like some
resource that dig deeper into the
concept and maybe like explain how it
works beneath and then a lot of like
when I try to focus on some new area or
something or have a new mostly it's
driven by like I find something and I
need to figure out the way to like
explode it or like it could this be a
problem or not and then I had to like
start uh like
building new building and testing and
and reading and digging deeper like into
that subject
so I it's kind of driven by what I find
mostly
and
um when you're hiking on gitlab uh
what's the indication for you that some
that it's worth spending more time on a
specific functionality
yeah so
I guess I I had the same experience as
most people do when they go to like a
new program like when I started gitlab
the first time I was like this seems
like a solid application there's
probably nothing here like I can click
all these buttons but yeah sure like how
would this break like I I hadn't really
like developed the the the sense of uh
like the hacker mentality yet nowadays
when I see like a new functionality my
first question is always like okay so
like how could this break
and I try to
go through like different scenarios like
how would this like how would this go
wrong like what could happen if this
goes wrong and stuff like that uh but uh
usually I just I click around the gitlab
interview face and I also read like uh
right like old disclose reports and also
sometimes like issues that come up uh in
their issue tracker and sometimes
there's just like some word or something
that is like triggering me uh to to dig
like deeper into that like functionality
and a lot of times it's like I see them
do something that like I haven't seen
that functionality and then I had like
uh Trace back like how do I reach that
part of the application
and sometimes obviously I know the
feeling when when you see in the code
that if you get up to here you will have
the bug and technically it's not hard
but it's hard to actually know how to go
in this application and actually trigger
this this part of the code
um some people test by
choosing one vulnerability class and
then going through all the target with
with a single vulnerability
some look at the source code finds
interesting things and then try to to
find out how can they get to to the sink
other people test functionally but d by
functionality uh obviously it's a mix
for everyone but how do you test
vulnerabilities
yeah so
I've in git lab I've had the most
success with like
um different kinds of injection like
front and the injection attacks kind of
so like everything from like HTML
injections and cross-site scripting and
some
um like path client side path traversals
and and stuff like that but uh
uh and also like information disclosures
but
so I've
my
my workflow is kind of like if I find
something that's like feel a bit weird I
start like digging into that one and
like starting to research about that
subject and then of course I try to see
if there are like other places in the
code base where they have made like
maybe the same mistake or something like
that but it's mostly like driven from
the functionality that I find like could
this be like injection
and in the action or could this be yes
like if I log in as like a user with a
different privilege maybe I could access
this page or uh whatever and uh
I have this goal of like diversifying
somewhat like trying to find like new
attack vectors uh I don't know if I will
manage to do it on gitlab I've been
lucky to to diversify a bit on other uh
programs where I've been like either
like invited to private programs and uh
some other I've also looked a bit at
browsers that's kind of my new new goal
looking at the Chrome and Firefox it's a
really fun fun challenge
um
but so so they're kind of like what what
type of attack you can look for
different like it differs depending on
the target I guess
and you mentioned that sometimes you
will find a
will you find the functionality or or
something that you want to see if it's
vulnerable in other places
when you want to to look for it do you
first
do some code search to find the same
let's say the same mistake in other
places of the code or do you think about
functionalities or how would you do this
so in gitlab it mostly I will find maybe
I will find something that works weird
and then I go to try to find this area
in the source code to see like that's
also great with this like white box or
gray box testing like white box in this
case that you don't have to like guess
what kind of payloads you can enter
there you can just go to the source code
and so maybe I find like okay I can
enter
some like my usually I just enter like
this H1 tag like H1
ASD uh closing
tag to just see if like it pops some or
if I can see that my text is actually
like rendered at HTML but then in gitlab
there's a lot of places where this is
allowed like markdown fields and
whatever so then I just go to the source
code and see like okay is this markdown
or is this something else and that you
can quite quickly see like uh what it is
and then if I realize like okay this is
an issue I try to escalate it and when I
have my report and I have my escalation
I've sent it in I try to like grab in
the source code for similar places where
they've used
maybe the same functionality or the same
function or something like that
what what IDE are you using to browse
the code
so yeah I saw someone like ask something
about it as well on the Twitter and
[Music]
to my I I should have been better with
this from the start I've been like a
late bloomer uh in this setting up like
a proper environment so I've actually
been browsing the code through the
gitlab
web page which is horrible because you
cannot like click on function to find it
you have to like search for it manually
and you have to load like a new page for
every directory you want to get into and
stuff like that and then I have improved
with this lately on GitHub you can yeah
exactly and you can get only the
browser-based visual studio code but
also the normal browsing of the code is
also much easier now oh yeah uh yeah but
of course I I should have just
downloaded it way earlier than I did and
now I have it locally and it's way
quicker to browse around I use vs code
for that I have downloaded Ruby mine
which is like the the peak IDE for Ruby
but I don't really know any Ruby so
but so I will try to use it and see if I
can get any success with it I know that
like the the some other people are using
that with great success do you like
debug the code
yeah I'm also using vs code I've but I
feel for it's great for go along it's
great for node.js but for Ruby i i a few
times already I was jumping to Ruby mind
because I know it's better uh vs code
doesn't always do the function that
jumps to function properly but I always
come back to vs code because I'm just
more familiar with it and
um and I go through the struggles but
when you are testing gitlab do you have
a local instance
uh yeah or I I do uh both uh kind of
depending on what I need to test like
some functionality is only available
in their like Cloud environment or like
on the gitlab.com page and some
functionalities only uh available in
your like local
local environment so I do a bit of both
it's also sometimes easier to test
locally because you don't have to care
about like CSP blocking your
exercises and stuff like that and then
you try to like get it to work on their
the real page as well
um
yeah on the gitlabs program if you
submit like three valid reports your
they will give you like an ultimate
trial license or like that you can use
locally for a year uh so that will also
make it possible for you to take so
that's like the third option having like
an ultimate license locally so then you
get access to like even more
functionality
um
and also if you want to test like dos
like denial of service things you have
to do it on your own machine you cannot
do it on the gitlab servers
is it a lot of effort to set it up and
maintain
uh no it's actually it's really easy to
just set up an instance you just copy
like a Docker script they have this
called like Omnibus uh like a Docker
image you start and everything is
running inside of there like all the
whatever is needed like background
processes and stuff and
so like databases and everything and
then you can just like update it and
keep the data locally and so that's
fairly simple
I feel like it's a bit trickier to set
up like
uh other like if you're gonna start like
your own gitla branders and stuff like
that and connect them uh
that's the the workers for like the CI
CD pipelines and stuff like that if you
want to like test those kind of features
it can be a bit more tricky that's also
like one of the that's why people don't
test those areas as much I guess like
when it starts to get like a lot of
build up before you can actually like
test a really small feature I've done a
lot of that lately like
thing up it's a really complicated stuff
it is one of the easiest ways to
differentiate from other hackers to just
spend more time on setting up and
reading the docs yeah but it's also like
a mess to send in the reports afterwards
because you have to tell like the
Creator to do all these steps it can be
really it can be a pain
yeah I I feel like
um with the the open source programs
it's sometimes hard to get past the
Trias because with developers you just
show the code and and you're speaking on
the same wavelengths because you both
know the code base but the three Azure
which is responsible for many programs
just doesn't have the
the knowledge that both you have and the
developers have and it's sometimes a bit
tricky to get through that phase but
once you get uh you can speak the same
language with develop developers yeah
also you mentioned
um client-side Parts reversal do you
have any disclosed Report with this
because I I also seen one report with
with this bug
yeah uh I actually have one that I I
realized that I haven't uh requested a
disclosure for it but it is public in
the the issue tracker
um so I can try to to link that one I
will also try to make it or ask them to
disclose it uh now uh it's uh
kind of the
or I've had some like similar bugs that
I have had a hard time to like um
the name properly like people are trying
to name these things in different ways
but uh it's this bug where I could like
do a path traversal and make some of the
buttons in the the UI interface like if
you click them they will make like a put
request to the API and and you can
yeah depending on who clicks it you can
do different things like evil
get yourself like to become an admin if
there is an admin clicking the button
and stuff like that
um
apart from setting up things that other
people don't want to set what do you
think you do that differentiates you
from from other hackers because
definitely before you started hacking on
gitlab both me and probably dozens of
other Hunters would say that no way
there are there is a way to jump up
gitlab's leaderboard quickly but you
just show that you can so what was the
secret what do you do differently
uh I think that I
I focus like quite heavily on even if I
report some uh like a lot of these UI
issues as well like my main focus is to
like understand the
uh the application and the like the
business logic part of it so a lot of
the bugs I find uh seem even to me like
quite simple like like this privileged
uh bypasses where you can like if I am
for example uh they have this concept of
an external user those were some of the
first bugs I found like during what I
did the thesis I tested like all this
trying to get my user into different
states so like if it's an external user
you're only supposed to see like
projects and groups that are that you
are a member of you you're not able to
see like other like internal or like
publicly internal projects uh
and then I always like so I have that in
the back of my mind all the time when I
see a new functionality like okay so who
can use this like what happens if I do
this as this kind of user or this kind
of user or this kind of user so I
started to like really try to build up
an understanding of like
how the the like the business logic of
gitlab was working I think that that
have helped me a lot because it also
makes me Focus Less on like the
technical Parts I guess there's like a
lot of like super talented hackers with
all these like knowledge about doing uh
like technical attacks that have tested
gitlab but then you can just find a way
to like leak some data because you're a
the user in this different setting of
the application and
so in this context by understanding the
business logic do you mean understanding
what
permission level what it means in a real
life what it means in a real company
um and if yes how do you keep track of
it how do you note these things
yeah so that's what I mean like having
an understanding of like what is
important for gitlab and what is
important for like the gitlab customers
like why there has been some reports
that I made that has been like so this
is like this information have been like
it's been in the UI for a long time and
I just I know that it shouldn't probably
be there because I that's how like my
understanding of it and then I report it
and they say like yeah you're right like
this shouldn't be here so they like
accept it like a an information
disclosure thing
um
and uh
so what was the the second part how do
you note it oh yeah yeah taking notes
yeah that's one of my other like on the
on the to-do list I have no notes at all
uh essentially
I I promised myself to start taking
notes like a couple of times but I I
haven't done it so I and it's horrible
like I have to re-discover things a lot
of times I can search for it again and
again and I've started taking some notes
of like payloads that I know work in
different situations uh just so I don't
have to like find them again the next
time I am
uh I I wouldn't recommend that at all
it's a horrible system but but it works
apparently it works
um coming back to your thesis I I
thought that it possibly could have
helped you because myself when I write
uh write some notes and I know that I
will publish them later for other other
people and more meticulous doing this
and I'm thinking to myself no if other
people read this will they think about
the scenario that I want and I will look
like a fool and I then come up with new
things to test
um do you think when you're doing your
thesis did you even note like why is a
part not vulnerable or was it also no
notes policy
uh yeah I should have taken more notes
uh at that time as well I guess uh and
I've been trying to force myself to do a
bit more writing and like taking notes
and trying to like explain stuff for
myself as well
um and as you say like that's also a way
that I often find bugs like I I see
someone like gitlab is like releasing
these uh like fixed issues like once a
month
and a lot of times I can like look at
someone else's report and
by like understanding like what they
have done
I can immediately start like thinking of
other like the like areas that they have
missed that are like really similar and
that's when my like the the
understanding of the whole like
application comes into play because
maybe I know something about this
different uh part of the application or
this the other like permission level
that will also cause a problem
so I try to do that with my own reports
usually by like it usually takes a month
or two to have them like through the
whole like Tree Art Product process and
usually I go go back to the reports and
like revisit them and try to see if I've
missed something and
like dig deeper into
and when you report it back
um do you like consider the job done and
you're just waiting for the payout or
are you tempted to come back to it maybe
escalate an impact find something else
uh that's uh it's interesting I've been
like meaning to put my opinions on that
like out somewhere on Twitter or
anywhere else but I I would like to stop
myself a lot of times I've seen a lot of
tweets and discussions about like a fire
and forget or like uh report and forget
I don't know what they say but like that
you should just report and move on yeah
and I think that might be like a good
advice if you're like
one of those people who are like having
tons of findings like working on
multiple programs and like do this for a
living or whatever
but for me it's like when I learn the
most and when I find the most like news
things is when I've had like one like
opening like something that like I found
this small bug then I can spend like a
lot of time trying to like escalate it
understand it see if there are like
other related things
so usually I come back to my reports
like a lot of times not just to look
like okay let's see if the triager has
answered me but I come back and like add
information
sometimes to the extent to like it
becomes like uh
a bit too much I guess like bloated and
sometimes they ask me to like yeah you
should just write a new report for this
so I've started to divide that map a bit
but so I I would say for like beginners
definitely not just like report and move
on because you have the opportunity like
really dig deep into a subject now when
you have like this entry point into the
application
uh yeah yeah I I agree with this and
gitlab is is obviously huge after
spending about one and a half years two
years on it now
how big part of it do you think you're
familiar with and uh are you aware of
all the different components that that
GitHub is composed of
yeah so I'm definitely not I'm like
familiar with like the the regular user
experience and the the UI parts and like
some parts of the the internal like
business logic layer but there's a lot
of
Parts in gitlab that is also like they
have their separate scope in their
backbending program like you're looking
at their like back-end Services
which would be probably you would need
like do even more like code research and
maybe like running these local systems
and test them but I I'm pretty sure that
they would accept bugs on the in those
areas as well uh so and I'm I've seen
like the the sketches and diagrams on
their like documentations of from these
systems but uh I haven't really looked
into them and there's also like some
parts that still scare me like setting
up like terraform clusters and stuff
like that that's also on my to-do list
so if someone beats me to it feel free
yeah that's that's what we've talked
about if you invest more time into doing
this scary setup things yeah which I'm
also very scary of then then it's a good
way to to differentiate
yeah and uh
you kind of mentioned uh at least one
thing but what do you think you waste
time on when hacking
definitely waste time on this like
clicking on the same functionality like
again and again uh when I like I'm when
I don't feel like inspired maybe I just
log in and I'm like okay let's go to the
project page again like maybe I missed
something and I just click on everything
and I I mean I shouldn't do that there's
like better ways to like more structural
ways to go through the application uh
and also the like not taking notes as I
said like that I would save a lot of
time by like having this more structured
way but I also feel like
the the wasting time is really hard to
to say that like that's what I'm doing
because all of a sudden I will find
something so it's kind of part of the
process just like linger around and uh
uh I guess be present in it I guess like
all of a sudden you see something and
you find
make a finding do you think having a
creative background uh helps you in any
way in coming up with attack scenarios
um no I mean it could I guess uh I like
like thinking like taking a concept and
like turning it around and upside down
and like inside out and trying to uh
really like dig into
that that goes for everything it doesn't
really have to be like bug boundary
related or like if I work and I do fine
like I'm encountering some kind of like
Tech
that I haven't used before I usually
just I want to like understand how it
works and I I spend a lot of time
watching YouTube videos uh getting like
into the deep weeds of that subject
whatever it is so and that definitely
helps because
then you will start to see like the
potential vulnerable points I guess
yeah yeah the reason I'm asking is
um
when I started doing creative things
like scripting a video or trying to come
up with with something
so a creative process in general I see
how much wasting time actually is the
best way to come up with something good
and before I would think about people
with creative jobs like I don't know
writers about people who just walk
around the home all day very lazy
and having a very hard job to to come up
with an interesting story and and it
switched my perspective that often as
I've said wasting time again again on
the same things uh is actually very good
for for creativity yeah and then
that you can like be smart about it and
like try to to force like
sometimes you have to spend those like
hours like banging your head against the
wall and then when you take a break you
will like finally understand something
so you need to take those hours you
cannot only take breaks but then
sometimes you take like way too many
hours I guess so you have to like try to
find a balance of like okay I should
stop now and then maybe I could figure
something out
[Music]
um
I've had some of those uh like the
classic like shower moments when I've
found bugs like while taking a shower uh
because I it's finally like clicks for
me like I was something can you talk
about what idea was that uh yeah like
one of my like first findings was like
that
um I kind of touched on it like it was
with this like external uh users like I
I found this functionality where you can
create like access tokens in your
project so like project level access
tokens and I was digging into that
functionality and it seemed like when
you created an access token it created a
user like a temporary like a bot user
and uh so I've been digging into that
and I also had been digging into this
external user thing uh and I then when I
took a shower I just unders like
realized that well if I create a token
with my external user I will get access
to this like Port user which is not
external
and I was really like excited it was
also very late I tried to go to sleep
but I couldn't I had to get up and test
it out and it worked so that's like in
the amazing feeling of like something
working like as you expected it to yeah
yeah exactly so that was great
I I've had this same experience with I
think my first debugging stripe which I
found
before recording the first episode of
the podcast I just came up with some
idea when I was not hacking but I didn't
jump to the computer because I thought
it won't work
and I Was preparing for the interview
with with David for the first episode as
I mentioned and
while I I had burp open I didn't
remember why but I was checking some
preparing for the podcast with better
popping so I I figured out I will just
give my idea a try and all of a sudden
it worked and so so I remembered oh no
it probably was before the second
episode
um never mind that it's a great feeling
you know yeah yeah it's awesome I
actually I think I should spend more
time doing nothing I'm like whenever I'm
bored or whenever I'm doing anything I
have headphones in my ears either
listening to a podcast audiobook
whatever
and I think I would benefit from
spending more time doing nothing yeah I
definitely have that experience as well
like yeah sometimes I I like fill up my
schedule way too much so I don't have
any time for
uh for those like
times for just thinking but my family is
really good like uh
forcing me out of
of uh thinking only about one subject
right
yeah exactly what I want to to get into
you have a full-time job of a developer
you have three kids how do you find time
for hunting
yeah so that's a of course a good
question uh
I've been cutting out of like everything
else except for like family and job I
guess like uh I don't play games anymore
or stuff like that like I like used to
do a couple of years ago so
I usually spend like one or two hours
almost each at least weekday uh at like
when my kids have gone to bed I do
something like bug Bounty related like
reading blogs or testing something or
something like that but usually
uh when I and I sometimes I also get
like a bit like a some more time on my
hands like maybe my family goes away for
a day or two or something I can get like
a couple more hours uh but uh I don't
have uh enough time to like dig super
deep so it's more like
that's also why I focus only mainly on
like one program and sticking to that
because when I have like only two hours
it's way easier to just get into
something that I'm familiar with and not
just trying to get into this like whole
new application of
uh but it's a it's a tricky balance I
guess I mean I have three kids uh to
take care of and they're quite intense
sometimes what they did are they they're
from like they're two and
five and six
now yeah so so that's probably very time
consuming yeah they are uh but I've also
I've found some bugs like while like
scrolling the phone laying on the floor
like waiting for them to fall asleep to
sleep and stuff like that so
maybe it also like forces me to look in
the different areas I guess
yeah maybe the the time of not doing
anything that's consuming their minds
too much which which also helps the
creative process
[Music]
um
so do you work full time actually yeah I
do I work as a
at the moment like a front-end developer
I would say uh
at this uh Swedish it's a actually now I
work at like a security related company
called recorded future they do like a
threat intelligence for other companies
um I guess that's the the main focus but
I mainly I'm so like I'm a front-end
developer so I build like react uh
direct application
[Music]
do you think about either going full
time with black Bounty or maybe reducing
your time spent in a let's say making
your job part-time to to have more room
for back Bounty yeah I mean of course
I've thought about it when I have had
these like weeks when it's been very
successful but I also have so I get
gitlab pays quite well for bugs so
that's why I sometimes have like a high
like I get a long like bounties for a
month but there's usually like a way a
long period in between finding them
and every time I don't find anything I
feel like oh I I could never do this
like full time and
yeah I mean I will
at the moment I'm really happy to like
building stuff at work and yes doing
this like as a hobby and not having
something like destroying it like making
it my career
uh I I think it's really fun uh last
year I kind of was focused on like
trying to prove to myself that I could
do it like I could consistently find
issues and I could like get paid for it
uh I was between jobs like during the
summer so that was when I had like most
time doing it and then during the fall
when I entered my new role I I haven't
had as much time
um to focusing on it
[Music]
so right now I've kind of shifted my
focus to try to like be a bit more like
structured and maybe do some other parts
like doing more like maybe do a write-up
or two or stuff like that like I I don't
feel I don't feel so stressed about
finding a lot of bugs uh so far like
this year because I I kind of proved it
to myself last year that it's possible
so now I know that at least so let's see
what the future brings I understand also
so you started uh writing a Blog and a
write-up of an exercise challenge yeah
so I have my my second right upcoming uh
on Monday I think uh so it's it's fun
it's where can people find it if we're
talking about it already I'm sorry yeah
I have uh trying to start a web page
uxcar.com so it's like blog.uxcar.com
um as you can find it there uh hopefully
I will add some more like
uh write-ups and stuff that is related
to my own work uh the I I kind of used
this like Integrity challenges just to
force myself to try to write something
and it really it helped like I started
the blog like set up this jacob page and
all that so I'm happy about it
and also
um you mentioned a long period of not
finding a bug one question is what's
your definition of long period of not
finding the bag because it differs very
much between different counters and the
second question is what do you do then
so I I have this I have tried to have
like at least one result report each
month
but that's like a not very accurate
measurement because it's sometimes your
reports they are likely reported this
one month and it gets like resolved way
later so but
like between findings I would say like a
month is a long period for me or it was
like that at least last year I could
usually find something each month in a
like some program maybe not gitlab but
uh like in some other like if you quote
like easier Target
[Music]
um
and what do we do then
I get into that like kind of dry period
I just
I don't know I just keep on going I
think uh just keep on like reading and
in git lab the easiest thing to do is
just wait for the next release which is
like the 22nd each month
and then you get some like new scope to
look at
um
but yeah I mean
before so now I think I have like over
50 resolved reports on the hacker one
and so before like the like the first
like 30 before that I was really like
um after each result report I still felt
like this is just luck like I cannot do
this like uh
it's a it has nothing to do with me like
me I've just been lucky so like I will
never find a bug again uh now I kind of
feel confident like if I look at
something like long enough I would
probably be able to find something so
that actually that helps like
uh with the
with your mental health I guess yeah
yeah I I feel exactly the same that that
in the beginning you just don't believe
it it can be this way but but after more
time you just get the the confidence and
uh and it gives you a calm look at the
periods of not finding back
yeah no sometimes I I get the idea to
like start looking at some new uh
program as well like I get some invite
or something or I I find something
interesting and then I kind of sometimes
feel again like yeah this is not like
I'm not good at this like there's
nothing here to find for me
so and then I have to like remind myself
like okay but it will take some time
like you have to really get into like
this program and to find something or be
lucky or like find something that I'm
good at so usually I find like xss stuff
unlike these random programs because I'm
fairly good at like
yeah the whole concept in JavaScript and
so
[Music]
yeah how do you choose other programs
because for for our viewers uh I think
if you look if we look at your public
hacker one profile there is only gitlab
yeah but I also see some private
programs which I'm also
accepted and I see that you are also
having a reasonable number of
submissions there so how do you choose
those programs what are you looking for
when choosing a program
I usually look at this like
not that they have like high bound this
in particular I usually look at like the
the medium level like if that is at
least like 500 or something so I know
that because that's what I usually find
uh sometimes I've like I try to escalate
it too high and if I'm lucky uh one
critical a year
but uh so I look at that and I I also
try to look at like what kind of company
is this but also like some of the
private invites I've jumped on are the
ones that I see like this is a real like
it's a fresh Target so then I enter to
be be part of this like gold rush in the
beginning so I've done that like once or
twice uh and it's a really like a
frustrating experience I think but it's
also fun because you find a lot of bugs
but uh like there's a lot of duplicates
and you have to write really shitty
shitty reports because you like have to
send them really quick
yeah exactly what I wanted to to I I
thought that if you're used to hacking
on gitlab with a relatively low amount
of bugs big payouts and detailed reports
then then taking part in a new program
is probably not not nice no it's really
different I mean when I find something
on gitlab
sometimes I don't like it can take some
days before I report it uh maybe I don't
have time to see that the computer like
it's a weekend that I have to go with my
family somewhere but I'm never like
stressed uh that someone else will
report it like either they would have
reported before or they would find it
like some days after like I have never
had like an issue that I reported
something and it was just like hours or
one or two days in between on gitlab at
least so but on this like gold rush
programs I've had those like yeah two
minutes and you can see like the the ID
is like yeah you're a duplicate of the
report that was reported previously
and probably a one or two Hunters
between it too yeah exactly so do you
have a lot of duplicates and and nice
and stuff like this
uh on the like gitlab is very friendly
they I think it's really hard to get
like an N A at the program they give
like informational uh so I have some
informational usually because we kind of
disagree on what like what this danger
or like they maybe they don't know about
it and it's like
they they normally like they planned it
like that's a it's a feature not a bug
kind of stuff uh and I've had a fair
like a 10 duplicates or something like
that
um
but not very many but uh
it does happen but it's happened a lot
more on like other programs like this uh
the the smaller ones like they are also
usually slower to fix issues so it's a
higher chance
for it to be a duplicate
how do you deal with reports where they
are marked as informational where you
still even after their argument you
still disagree with this
I try to I've done that like a lot of
times sometimes I've succeeded to have
them accept it uh it's usually a really
long process like I don't know how the
system on hike one works when you send
something on like a an already closed
report it feels like it can take months
to get an answer
um
no sometimes I've
[Music]
yeah so I usually like asking and try to
get someone to know I've used this
feature on hacker one like one or two
times it's a moderation thing I probably
used it the wrong way uh and uh
one time I succeeded and one time it
nothing happened so
[Music]
um
but I mean it's a really tough one you
know like you you report a cross-site
scripting for example I kind of knew
like that I I reported one that was a
duplicate uh two months ago to gitlab
and I know that the the
issue is worth like twelve thousand
dollars or something like that they pay
now for like a CSP bypass xss
uh I kind of felt like okay this will be
a duplicate because it was very inspired
by another report uh and yeah he did
manage to to see like the bypass before
me and send it into
but like the way there is could be
frustrating
yeah yeah it's it it must hurt I haven't
had this case yet but I imagine it must
hurt
if a beginner let's say with a similar
background to you which is computer
science university and no professional
experience would tell to you asking
how to start back Bounty what would you
recommend them to do
I would
I mean I would probably be boring and
say like go to port swiger and like to
the labs and stuff like that
but I haven't really done that myself so
it's I don't know if it's good to twice
I would say like to find something that
interests you like you have to like feel
a connection with the program and you
have to feel a connection with the bug
types you're hunting for otherwise it
will become really boring really fast
like you will you will not be able to
like stick through it like I spend a lot
of time like trying to understand how
HTML and xss stuff work because I think
it's really fun yes it's like a puzzle
game and you have to have that like
you have to feel happy about doing it
otherwise it will just become
yeah it will become way too boring I
think
is this your favorite bug class the
exercise
it's not I don't know if it's it is like
it's not really a good one to have like
your favorite because uh it's a lot of
programs yes put it as a medium and you
have to spend like a lot of time trying
to escalate it and stuff I think idors
are like better you just give them like
here's the end point it leak all the
data
and you're done yeah but I like it
because it has this like puzzle aspect
to it and it also gives you like a white
box testing feeling even on like black
box environments because you can always
look at this at the source code and like
try to
to figure out like how you would bypass
something and trying to find like
I mean I don't like it in a way it is
like
paste the payload and see if it pops up
I like when you have to like dig into
the HTML and see if you can find like a
gadget somewhere and use it in some
interesting way and I've had a lot of
success on the like older programs like
private ones but you I can see that a
lot of people have been there and then I
just opened their kind of like they have
some sort of like HTML Builder included
and I've found like a lot of exercises
in them because it's really fun to like
try to bypass this uh filters they have
in place and I'm I guess most people
just put in some payloads and moved on
when it didn't work
when you're hacking and you see that
um let's say you're in gitlab and you
find the functionality and you get to a
point where you'll think
if you find the vulnerability here it's
a bug in the library and not in gitlab's
code in this situation do you like
assume the library is secure or you
don't want to test the library or you
dig deep and check out the source code
of the library now I definitely wouldn't
check out the source code of the library
I mean gitlab is good in that regard as
well like they will pay you for a third
party bugs if you find find them like
when hunting on their program
so but I would definitely try to
but so that's what how I found my I have
like one
bug that is uh resolved in the Firefox
it was this like not super serious like
you could execute the uh JavaScript in
like a sandboxed iframe sort of but you
had to like really mess up your code for
it to happen but they still accepted it
and because I found it on a program
where they had done this so I could
execute like my my payload it fired on
Firefox but not on any other browser so
their code like it was not very well
written but I mean they used it in a way
that should be safe so I reported it to
uh to Mozilla and I I got like a a way
higher Bounty for them like I got 2 000
from musila for it and I got like 200 or
something from the company where I found
it because I did yeah I mean I didn't
have to tell them like the browser is
gonna fix this because I I thought the
code was pretty
they needed to fix it anyway I guess so
yeah
is this what you're looking forward in
2023 into more browser hacking yeah
definitely it has some of the same
feeling as with gitlab I I feel like
everything is open source you can read
all the disclosed bugs in like Chrome
and stuff like that and you can also
like you just sit in your browser and
build stuff uh like trying to use the
web API since uh trying to so that's how
I'm gonna approach this browser testing
I'm not gonna go in and finding like
buffer overflow things uh which people
seem to find are like use of the free
seems to be like
big issues Synchro so I'm not going to
be so technical
so what bugs will you look into and what
are the skills required for this
uh I mean
the the browsers are using like they are
implementing web apis so they are
essentially as like applications just
like gitlab and
sometimes they get things wrong I mean
you can read the the specification and
you can try it out and you can see if
they follow the specification and I've
done a lot of like testing with these
iframes like and it's really fun because
you can do it in your own like small web
page you create an iframe and you just
throw stuff at it and see if it breaks
in some way like uh and there's tons of
apis
in the like the web framework and
it's yeah I mean you can test it just
like any other application so that's
what I'm planning to do and I've found
as I said like I have
I have one bug in the Chrome that is
fixed but it will be disclosed in like
two weeks or something I think and I
will try to write the write up for it
hopefully and I have another one in
Firefox which is like pending
so it's not and those areas like
api-ish related bugs in this like web
in their yeah the web implementations
so my last question what's the reason to
disclose your findings
um in theory you are just making
yourself a competition so so what's
what's the reason for for publishing for
writing blog posts disclosing findings
and coming to us on podcasts as well
yeah I know so my wife asks me this as
well like why why do you do this like
aren't you just
this sharing your secrets and losing out
on it but I don't know I think it's I
feel like it's part it's partly because
I I feel like obligated to give back
like I've learned everything I know from
other people who have shared their
knowledge so I feel like it's nice to do
the same
but I also feel like that's like the
when I get tired of like finding a
hunting for bugs like in a technical
perspective it's really nice to have
like this
is you start building up uh something
like which is also outside of the bug
hunting so I I get contacted by
people sometime they like ask me like I
found this we maybe we could try
something together and then I I mean
there's like this
things happen when you start like
putting yourself out there I guess I've
gotten like your buffers and stuff like
that as well so uh
that's mainly I want to share it and I
also want to to
make myself like present
it's in the community I guess
okay I understand uh thank you so much
for for joining me in this interview I
think there is there are tons of value
for for our viewers um if people want to
follow you where can they find you
so I'm uh on Twitter you wax car I'm
also at Mastodon which is the new place
to be I guess uh so I'm ux card there as
well like uh infosec exchange and then I
have my new blog and I also have
LinkedIn and gitlab and GitHub and
everything I have the same handle so I
guess you can search for me if you want
to find me but if you want to reach out
you do it on Twitter it's easiest like
DM perfect it's
j-o-a-x-c-a-r for for those that are
listening yeah and once again thank you
for joining me
thank you thank you for having me
[Music]
thank you for listening to the whole
episode if you enjoyed it leave a like
on YouTube or a review on Apple podcast
or Spotify I'm also open to any feedback
you have and suggest me future guests
that you would like me to interview for
now thank you for listening and goodbye
[Music]